{
    "tossups": [
        {
            "question": "Baudez and Latsanopoulos have interpreted two panels as representing the training and graduation of jaguar warriors under the guidance of a jaguar-serpent-man in this city\u2019s Temple of the Wall Panels. Ostensibly avenging the theft of the wife of the ruler of an allied city, Hunac Ceel [\u201cwho-KNOCK kale\u201d] conquered this city and entered one of its holy spaces seeking a prophecy, despite everyone else he had sent in not reemerging. Carvings in this city\u2019s Temple of the Warriors depict Toltec soldiers scouting out and then invading the city; that invasion has been used as the dividing line between \u201cOld\u201d and \u201cNew\u201d versions of this city. Augustus Le Plongeon coined the term (*) \u201cChacmool\u201d after unearthing one such statue in this city. Gold, obsidian, and human remains are among the offerings made into this city\u2019s namesake Sacred Cenote [say-NO-tay]. For 10 points, what is this Maya city of the northern Yucatan known for its Temple of Kukulkan, also known as \u201cEl Castillo\u201d?",
            "answer": "Chich\u00e9n Itz\u00e1",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "The relative ease with which slaves, and particularly slave women, could acquire fine clothes in the capital of this colony led to a 1735 \u201cNegro Act\u201d prohibiting slaves from receiving their masters\u2019 discarded clothes. The virtue in applying Christian doctrine to \u201ctrivial\u201d daily matters and the equality of women before God was argued by the Quaker Sophia Hume in her An Exhortation to the Inhabitants of [this colony]. Elizabeth Timothy worked with Benjamin Franklin to publish this colony\u2019s first successful newspaper. Slave women\u2019s familiarity with farming the (*) glaberrima variety of one crop in Africa allowed it to become an important commodity in this colony after first being cultivated there by Henry Woodward. Eliza Lucas established indigo as a cash crop in this colony. For 10 points, what is this colony, whose namesake Gazette Timothy printed from its capital, Charleston?",
            "answer": "South Carolina",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Pliny the Elder claimed that this material was accidentally discovered by Phoenician traders near the mouth of the Belus River. A 2016 paper by Boschetti et al posits that the city of Aquileia was a recycler of this material, rather than a producer of it as has been traditionally believed. The Wadi El Natrun was an important source for an ingredient used to lower the melting point of this material. Gold was sometimes sandwiched between two layers of this material in early Christian art and Byzantine mosaics to increase the gold\u2019s (*) luster. The modern city of Trier is believed to have been a center for the production of cage cups, which were primarily made of this material. One theory proposes that artisans fleeing the foreign invasions at the end of the Roman Empire established a center for producing this material on the island of Murano near Venice. For 10 points, what is this material, which saw a proliferation of the \u201cblowing\u201d production technique during the Roman Empire?",
            "answer": "glass\u00a0",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "The Book of Zambasta, a philosophical and literary collection of this religion, complains that the language it is written in was not widely considered an appropriate medium for transmitting this religion. Mentions in ancient documents of a god named Bhatro suggest syncretism of this religion with local traditions in the Shanshan Kingdom. The 1902 \u014ctani Expedition excavated numerous sites related to this religion, such as the Kizil and Kumtura Caves near Kucha. Before attaining great power as viziers to the early Abbasid caliphs, the (*) Barmakid family were leaders in this religion\u2019s sites at Nawbah\u0101r in Balkh. The Hellenistic art styles that followed the conquests of Alexander the Great led to the first known depictions of this religion\u2019s founder in sculpture and on coins in places like the Greco-Bactrian Kingdom and the Kushan Empire. For 10 points, what is this religion brought to Central Asia along the Silk Road from South Asia?",
            "answer": "Buddhism (accept H\u012bnay\u0101na Buddhism or Mah\u0101y\u0101na Buddhism; do not accept or prompt on \u201cTherav\u0101da Buddhism\u201d)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A youth subculture in 1950\u2019s Kinshasa was collectively named after this man, from which the Hindoubill [an-doo-BILL] argot [ar-\u201cGO\u201d] developed. Augusto Imperiali became a hero in his home town of Cisterna [chees-TARE-nah] di Latina after leading a group of butteri in defeating this man in a competition. Following this man\u2019s visit to Karlsruhe, the residents of its S\u00fcdstadt district have been nicknamed \u201cIndians\u201d. While on a hunting trip with this man during his tour of the US, Grand Duke Alexei Alexandrovich borrowed this man\u2019s horse (*) Buckskin Joe. Using a gun he named after Lucrezia Borgia, this man defended his right to his nickname in a hunting competition against a man with the surname Comstock. This man is best known for running a touring show featuring the likes of Annie Oakley and Sitting Bull. For 10 points, who was this man who ran an eponymous \u201cWild West\u201d show?",
            "answer": "William Frederick \u201cBuffalo Bill\u201d Cody (accept either underlined portion)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A city is described in this work as \u201cmistress of the navigation of a hundred rivers\u201d, and later that city\u2019s influence from Bentham and Rousseau is compared to another city\u2019s reliance on conservative \u201ccommentators\u201d, the Catholic Church, and the Jesuits. In the second chapter of this book, \u201cOriginality and Peculiarities of the People\u201d, professions like the baqueano [ba-kay-ah-noh] and cantor are described. A figure in this work ignores Dr. Ortez\u2019s assassination warning and is killed by Santos P\u00e9rez at Barranca-Yaco. This work contains a lengthy discussion of (*) \u201cThe Revolution of 1810\u201d, as well as descriptions of cities such as San Juan and Cordoba. The civil war between the Federales and Unitarios is central to this book. The main figure of this book is a caudillo [kaw-dee-yoh] from La Rioja nicknamed the \u201cTiger of the Plains\u201d, and it was written in part to condemn Juan Manuel de Rosas. For 10 points, name this 1845 book, subtitled \u201cCivilization and Barbarism\u201d, a work by Argentine president Domingo Sarmiento.\u00a0",
            "answer": "Facundo: Civilization and Barbarism (accept Facundo: Civilizaci\u00f3n y Barbarie)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Along with Sidney Webb, one politician with this first name rewrote the Labour party platform to be more explicitly socialist in 1918. That politician with this first name won the 1934 Nobel Peace Prize after chairing the World Disarmament Conference. A prime minister with this first name faced demonstrations in Hyde Park after importing over 60,000 laborers from China to work in South African gold mines. That politician with this first name gave a report at the 1926 (*) Imperial Conference which advocated for constitutional equality between Britain and its dominions. A politician with this first name succeeded his uncle Lord Salisbury as British Prime Minister in 1902, and that politician\u2019s best-known action as Foreign Secretary was authoring a 67-word statement concerning a \u201cnational home\u201d that was contained in a letter to Walter Rothschild. For 10 points, give this first name of a British politician who supported the creation of a Jewish homeland in a 1917 \u201cDeclaration\u201d.",
            "answer": "Arthur (accept Arthur Balfour or Arthur Henderson; Prompt on just their last names)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A visitor to this man\u2019s court claimed that his capital was founded by Herakles, who was particularly worshipped by the \u201cSourasenoi\u201d. According to Justin, this man\u2019s rise to power supposedly began after offending Alexander the Great; after running away and falling asleep from fatigue, a lion gently woke him by licking away his sweat. Later native sources describe this man\u2019s conclusion of peace with a Greek ruler involving his marriage to a Yona princess. That account also claims that later, as a leader of a group of bandits, an (*) elephant presented itself as a mount to this man, foreshadowing his later power. The elephants used at the Battle of Ipsus came from the peace negotiations this ruler had with Seleucus I Nicator. Visited by the ambassador Megasthenes, for 10 points, identify this ruler, commonly known to the Greeks as Sandrocottus, the founder of the Mauryan Empire.",
            "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya (accept Chandragupta on its own after \u201cMauryan\u201d is read; accept Sandrocottus before mentioned; prompt on \u201cChandragupta\u201d, but do not accept or prompt on \u201cChandragupta I\u201d or with any other regnal number)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Two answers required A 1913 friendship treaty between these two ethnic groups endorses the leader of one as a \u201cmaster of the Yellow faith.\u201d The warlord Godan from one of these ethnic groups was supposedly cured of a serious disease by Sakya Pa\u1e47\u1e0dita during an attack against the other ethnic group. The officials who governed over one of these ethnic groups on behalf of a dynasty of the other were called p\u00f6nchens. After meeting with a religious leader from one of these ethnic groups, a warlord of the other founded the Erdene Zuu monastery. (*) Drog\u00f6n Chagyal Phagpa, a member of one of these two ethnic groups, created an eponymous script to assist a dynasty of the other, the Yu\u00e1n. For 10 points, name these two ethnic groups, one the founders of Gelug Buddhism and the other containing the T\u00fcmed and Oirat khans who protected it.",
            "answer": "Tibetans and Mongolians",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "This language family is sometimes believed to have been influenced by the Maglemosian and Funnelbeaker cultures. An inscription on the Negau Helmet may be the earliest instance of a name written in a language from this family. This is the largest language family to feature predominantly verb-second word order. A language that belonged to this family was described by Ogier [oh-GEER] Ghiselin de Busbecq \u00a0[BOOS-beck] and went extinct in Crimea in the late seventeenth century. Anomalous proto-words of this language family, such as bainam and beron, are explained in this language family\u2019s (*) \u201csubstrate hypothesis\u201d. The Ulfila Bible is an important source for one language in this family, while another was written with an alphabet system known as the Elder Futhark. This language family includes Northern and Western branches, as well as an extinct Eastern branch, and its consonant changes are noted by Grimm\u2019s law. For 10 points, name this family of languages that includes Dutch and English.\u00a0",
            "answer": "Germanic language family (prompt on \u201cIndo-European\u201d language family; The proto-words bainam and beron are English for brain and bear, respectively)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Fraudulent games called \u201clototrons\u201d or \u201clokhotrons\u201d first emerged during this decade. In just a few years, the life expectancy in one country fell dramatically from 70 to 64 during this decade\u2019s \u201cmortality crisis\u201d credited to psychological stress. Almost 200 people died in street fights during a constitutional crisis in this decade, discussed in the Letter of the Forty-Two, after a president declared a \u201cspecial regime\u201d to grant himself powers to bypass parliament. A failed coup that opposed reforms made in this decade was attempted by a group called the (*) Gang of Eight. While discussing the swift privatization during this decade under Prime Minister Yegor Gaidar, Naomi Klein popularized the term \u201cshock therapy\u201d, a process which allowed the Russian oligarchs to seize huge amounts of previously state-owned assets. For 10 points, name this decade, in which Russia was subject to fast privatization after the fall of the Soviet Union.",
            "answer": "1990s",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "The most famous work of Ish\u0101q bin Ali al-Rohawi applied the concept of adab to this profession. The Bukhtishu family, originally from Jundishapur, produced many notable people in this profession during the Umayyad and early Abbasid Caliphates. Though this profession is not necessarily religious, the Qalawun Complex contains a large facility for practicing it. Throughout much of the Islamic world, many people in this profession worked in bimaristans. Al-Razi went against the common practice of this profession by writing the (*) Shukuk \u2018ala Jalinus, a critique on Classical work in this profession. Aristotle\u2019s four causes were applied to this profession in a \u201cCanon\u201d named after it by Avicenna. For 10 points, what is this profession that the medieval Islamic world built on from the work of Galen and Hippocrates?",
            "answer": "medicine (accept physicians, apothecaries, doctors, or any other such answers that suggest that they were in the business of keeping people healthy)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A resident of this place noted that when he traveled around it, there would be a servant who acted as a \u201cmotor horn\u201d, repeating the syllable \u201cchir\u201d to clear the path. To counter the theft of the collections of this place by its employees, Reginald Johnston encouraged an inventory of its items, leading to part of this place being set on fire. In a likely distorted account by Edmund Backhouse, Consort Zh\u0113n was pressured to drown herself in a well in this place. The earth removed in the construction of the moat around this place was used to create J\u01d0ngsh\u0101n Hill, the place where the (*) Ch\u00f3ngzh\u0113n Emperor committed suicide. Dorgon officially took the title of Prince-Regent in the W\u01d4y\u012bng Palace at this place after much of it was burned by L\u01d0 Z\u00ecch\u00e9ng (tsuh-chung). After the fall of the Q\u012bng Dynasty, P\u01d4y\u00ed was required to live in this place until 1924. For 10 points, what is this palace complex in the center of B\u0115ij\u012bng?",
            "answer": "Forbidden City (accept G\u00f9g\u014dng; prompt on \u201cImperial City\u201d; prompt on \u201cB\u0115ij\u012bng\u201d before mentioned)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "The dissatisfaction a participant in this program had with his living conditions was made public in a press report citing his dislike of \u201crubberized chicken\u201d. Seven participants in this program were relocated to the town of Louisiana, Missouri to work in a converted ammonia plant. George Frenkel claimed that he \u201cnever compromised [his] humanity\u201d as an interrogator of, among others, participants in this program at P.O. Box 1142. The Osenburg List informed this program after portions of it were found stuffed in a (*) Bonn University toilet. Originally known as Operation Overcast, many of those selected to participate in this program had previously worked at Peenem\u00fcnde [\u201cpay\u201d-nuh-\u201cMOON\u201d-duh] developing the V-2 rocket. For 10 points, what was this program that brought scientists like Wernher von Braun to the US?",
            "answer": "Operation Paperclip (accept Operation Overcast before mentioned)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Over 200 nobles were tried in this city for their real or purported involvement in the Wessenlenyi (VESH-\u201cshell\u201d-en-yee) Conspiracy. In the early 1440\u2019s, the Rozgonyi family held this city\u2019s castle in support of W\u0142adys\u0142aw (vwah-dee-\u201csuave\u201d) III\u2019s claim to the Hungarian throne while the town supported Ladislaus the Posthumous\u2019 claim. G\u00e1bor Bethlen\u2019s final revolt against the Habsburgs for their ill-treatment of Protestants was ended with a treaty signed in this city. After the loss of Buda to the Ottomans, the coronation of most of the Monarchs of Hungary took place in this city\u2019s (*) St. Martin\u2019s Cathedral until Francis Joseph in 1867. A treaty signed in this city led to Austria\u2019s withdrawal from the Third Coalition and Francis II\u2019s renunciation of German territory, leading to the dissolution of the Holy Roman Empire soon after. For 10 points, what is this city, the capital of modern Slovakia?",
            "answer": "Bratislava (accept Pressburg or Pozsony)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A powerful chieftain in this modern country initially rejected the Christian Church, known locally as lotu, after being told that his doing so would not result in special treatment from English missionaries. A multicultural shipbuilding industry, in which the construction of a drua was celebrated with human sacrifice and feasting, was found in this country\u2019s Lau Islands. Economic and social issues, such as the establishment of a branch of the KKK, led to this country becoming a British colony shortly after being first unified by Thakombau. A 19th century chieftain from this modern country, Ratu (*) Udre Udre (oon-dray oon-dray), is purported to have been the world\u2019s most prolific cannibal. It\u2019s not in the Caribbean or Africa, but a Hindi-based language developed in this country after Indian laborers were imported as agricultural workers. For 10 points, name this Melanesian country now governed from Suva.",
            "answer": "Republic of Fiji\u00a0",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "After defeating an enemy\u2019s \u201clockstep legions\u201d, this city established a penal colony at Gorgossos, where slave women were used to create half-human, half-animal hybrids. A former colony of this city permits only Old Blood families to live within the Black Wall. The triumph of this city in five wars against its first rival was often shown with the death in combat of a harpy. Inventories, a book written by Thurgood, accounts for only 227 weapons made in this city. Losing to this city in the Second Spice War forced Queen (*) Nymeria to flee on 10,000 ships with the remaining Rhoynar. The empire created by this city fell when the sudden eruption of the Fourteen Flames brought about its namesake \u201cdoom\u201d, which also killed most of the world\u2019s dragons. The Targaryens are the most notable surviving noble house descended from, for 10 points, what former city of southern Essos?",
            "answer": "Old Valyria",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "The most flogged soldier in British Army history, who received 30,000 lashes over 14 years, was a drummer stationed at a British outpost near this country. The castle of Eilean Donan was to be the main Scottish base of one invasion of the UK by this country. Sorley Boy MacDonnell is believed to have taken some cannons off a ship from this country to arm his castles at Dunluce and Glenarm. The Battle of Glen Shiel ended one of this country\u2019s attempts to destabilize the UK. Storms prevented Jacobite James FitzJames Butler, Duke of Ormonde\u2019s attempt to lead a (*) 1719 invasion of the UK by this country. Though England had allied with this country at an earlier battle at the same place, English forces ended a threat of invasion by this country at Gravelines by the Duke of Medina Sidonia. For 10 points, identify this country, which sent a namesake armada in 1588 to invade England.",
            "answer": "Kingdom of Spain",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Descriptive answer acceptable After undergoing this action and living at Parramatta for five years, some accounts claim that Charlotte Badger led a mutiny on the Venus before being abandoned on an island by the other mutineers. Mary and William Bryant sailed to Timor in an open boat after undergoing this action and were defended in doing so by James Boswell. The Rajah Quilt was created by women undergoing this action using supplies donated through the work of Lydia Irving, a close associate of (*) Elizabeth Fry. Ross and Cascades were among the \u201cFemale Factories\u201d created by this action. 173 women underwent this action via the aptly named First Fleet, which in January 1788 arrived in Botany Bay. For 10 points, what is this action where the British government sent their criminals to a continent on the opposite side of the world?",
            "answer": "penal transportation to Australia (accept any answer that suggests that British people are being sent to Australia against their will; prompt on partial answers that convey only imprisonment/punishment or going to Australia)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Some of the miracles attributed to this ruler include the raising of Alice Newnett from the dead and the blinding of John Robyns. During this ruler\u2019s reign, a rebel leader won a battle at Sevenoaks and executed the lord treasurer James Fiennes. This ruler compelled nobles such as the Earl of Salisbury and the Duke of Exeter to hold hands during a \u201cloveday\u201d procession. The regency council of this ruler was headed by the Duke of Bedford and the Duke of (*) Gloucester. Jack Cade\u2019s rebellion took place during this ruler\u2019s reign, and after learning of the loss of Bordeaux, he suffered a yearlong mental breakdown. This ruler was briefly restored to the throne by his wife, Margaret of Anjou, and the Earl of Warwick, but soon lost the throne again after the Battle of Tewkesbury. For 10 points, name this Lancasterian king who lost his throne to the Yorkist Edward IV during the Wars of the Roses.\u00a0",
            "answer": "Henry VI of England",
            "category": "History"
        }
    ],
    "bonuses": []
}